[Music]
Meet Mr. Archimedes of ancient Greece.
Long ago, Aris said, "Give me a lever
long enough and I can move the world."
What Archimedes meant was that the power
of a lever is practically unlimited.
Today, almost everyone uses some form of
lever in his daily work. The familiar
can opener is a lever with a sharp
cutting edge. The playground seesaw is
just a simple lever, too. It takes a lot
of force to start a freight car moving.
Yet, the railroad man can start the
heaviest freight cars easily with a
pinch bar, a powerful lever which turns
the wheel.
Tough luck, old boy. Here's a place
where a lever comes in mighty handy.
Let's take the simplest kind of lever, a
rigid bar working on a fixed support
called a fulcrum. One end of this lever
is twice as long as the other. Let's put
a 10 lb weight on this end. And now
we'll put half as much weight on this
end. 5 lb balance 10.
If we have 25 lb to lift, we just use a
longer lever. The five lbs will now
balance five times as much. Let's raise
the lever in the air.
Change its shape a little and we have a
crank. Or we can add a second lever and
have a double crank. Now the short arm
moves 1/4 the distance, but we get four
times the force. If we want continuous
motion, we need more arms.
Now we have levers that turn.
The larger paddle wheel makes fewer
turns, but it delivers more force.
A paddle wheel is nothing but a
neverending series of levers. We can
make the wheels stronger and lessen
friction where the wheels touch each
other by rounding off the edges and
shaping them into teeth that will slide
in and out smoothly. Now the power flows
smoothly and continuously through
spinning leverage of gear wheels. Gears
are made in many kinds and many sizes.
Little gears, big gears, worm gears,
bevel gears, and even lopsided gears.
Over a 100 million gears are spinning
over the roads in the transmissions of
our automobiles.
The transmission is located right at the
bottom of the gear shift lever.
Let's start from scratch and put
together a model of the gears that we
shift in our motor car. The shaft on the
left comes from the engine. The shaft on
the right carries the power back to the
rear wheels. To connect these two with
gears, we'll need another shaft known as
a counterhaft.
These two gears carry the power from the
engine shaft to the counterhaft and are
always connected or in mesh.
This gear on the drive shaft going to
the wheels
is free to turn around the shaft.
We'll put it in mesh with another gear
on the counterhaft.
These gears are always in mesh
and keep turning while the engine is
running.
To switch from one set of gears to
another, our transmission needs a short
shaft like this, known as a clutch
sleeve.
It cannot turn on the drive shaft, but
it is free to slide back and forth.
On the sleeve, we'll mount a large gear,
which we can shift back and forth to
mesh with the small gear in the middle
of the counterhaft.
We are now in neutral. The gears that
are always in mesh are turning over with
the engine, but the shaft to the rear
wheels is standing still. A 3,000lb
automobile takes a lot of force to
start.
So in low speed, we get the greatest
leverage by letting the smallest gear on
the counterhaft turn the largest gear on
the drive shaft.
The engine on this model is running at a
constant speed of 90 revolutions a
minute.
With low gears in mesh, the rear wheel
is turning at 30 revolutions a minute.
About a third the speed of the engine,
but with three times the force. The
power is going through these gears in
the transmission.
After we've started the car rolling, we
want fast pickup. So, we shift into
second by sliding the sleeve backward to
mesh with this gear on the shaft to the
rear wheels. The wheel is now turning at
60 revolutions a minute and the power
flows through these gears.
For higher speeds, we let the power go
directly to the rear wheels.
We shift the sleeve forward
so that it meshes with the shaft from
the engine.
The power travels straight from the
engine to the drive shaft.
Now the shaft to the wheels is turning
at 90 revolutions a minute, the same
speed as the engine. But here's a
problem. An automobile must be able to
go backward as well as forward. So we
add one more set of gears to reverse the
shaft to the rear wheels. With the gears
shifted into reverse,
the power travels through the
transmission in a path like this.
We now have three sets of spinning
levers for going forward and one for
reverse. With a gear shift lever, we can
shift to any set of gears we wish.
But with all these spinning levers in
the transmission came noise and wear.
Experts could shift gears quietly by
careful timing of the gear shift and the
engine speeds, but most of us made
plenty of noise until new engineering
developments made possible the long
series of improvements that followed.
When we shifted gears, we got a clash
because the gears were not running at
the same speed. In other words, not
synchronized.
So engineers set to work to develop a
synchronizer. The synchronizer works
like a cork twisted into the top of a
bottle. The cork will turn until it is
so tight that the bottle turns with it.
Synchro mesh works the same way. When we
shift into second or high, the
synchronizer brings the gears to the
same speed before they come together.
The drums won't let the gears shift
unless they are turning at the same
speed.
When the gears come together, there is
no clash and the shift is made quietly
and easily.
In the transmission of the up-to-date
automobile, we have a powerful low gear
to give us a strong spinning leverage in
starting. A fast turning motor must set
the weight of the car in motion.
In second speed, we can change leverage
to get going fast at the same engine
speed. With the leverage of third gear,
power goes directly to the rear wheels,
and we can go as fast as we want. Now,
every driver can shift gears at any
time, regardless of speed. Here is a
hill that will give us a real chance to
see how smoothly and reliably our
spinning levers work in our automobile
transmission.
This driver is going to let her car gain
a speed of 60 m an hour down the hill.
[Music]
Then she will shift into second speed
and bring her car easily and safely
under control before it reaches the
bottom of the hill.
[Music]
Yeah.